Bill Blessing

Java Engineer – Spring Developer https://wblessing.atlassian.net

SUMMARY

Information Technology experience in the areas of system design, development and implementation, using structured project management. Primary strengths include object oriented development, enterprise middleware, database design, java web interfaces and Agile project strategies.

Languages	Java, HTML, CSS, XML, JSP
Frameworks	JEE, Spring, Hibernate
UI	JSF, Facelets, JSP, Servlets, Spring MVC
OS	Linux, Windows, Mac OSX
Servers	Tomcat, TomcatEE, JBoss, WebLogic
Databases	Postgres, Oracle, MySql, DB2
Tools	JIRA, Crucible, Nexus, Bamboo, Maven, Gradle, Sonar, Jenkins
Source Control	Git, Subversion, CVS
Methodology	ISO 9000, SDLC, Agile, UML

EXPERIENCE

Cognizant

Software Engineer

December 2017 - August 2019

Software developer for Cognizant group focused on Spring cloud development along with Angular user interfaces. The work included both internal and external projects with the Netflix cloud projects now being transitioned to Spring Cloud code base. The experience involved discussions and practice on avoiding the creation of new monoliths by limiting direct access to legacy data with a preference to legacy web services instead. Development environment includes linux Mint, Intellij, Spring Boot, and Jenkins, Gradle, Git.

- Spring Eureka Discovery
- Spring Config Server
- Feign Client
- Zul proxy
- Spring Rest
- Spring HATEOUS
- Spring Data

Infosys

Software Engineer / Contractor

April 2017 - December 2017 (8 months)

Software developer for a large financial institution in transition to a Restful façade using micro services to front end a large number of legacy web services. Updated onboarding documentation and created a Sharepoint wiki site to assist team transition from storing project details in email to a central wiki where all the team has view and update access.

- Spring MVC with JSPs
- Support Contract First WSDL services
- Create Java Spring RS services
- Git, Maven
- Eclipse EE with JRebel

Judge Group

Software Engineer / Contractor

October 2017 - March 2017 (6 months)

Assisted with the planning and migration of a Fortune 100 company SOA code base from Subversion to Git. Reconciled the two source control systems in order to identify services not migrated. Streamline the onboarding process of new software engineers by documenting specific LDAP groups for baseline developers and provided clearly documented steps in Confluence along with removing duplicate and misleading wiki information.

- Java Spring Core and Spring RS
- Subversion, Git, Maven, and Gradle
- Tomcat Server.
- SQL Server with Hibernate
- Jira and Confluence

Apptricity Corporation

Java Engineer

April 2016 - August 2017 (17 months)

Performed enhancements, production support, and performance enhancements for a Corporate Expense reporting and inventory tracking system. The system is based on Spring, Hibernate, and ZK for the user interface. Played a key role in implementing Flyway in order to establish a baseline database in support of automated testing using Selenium test framework.

- The implementation of Flyway provided a database baseline allowing automated QA tests to be developed.
- The application is deployed to Tomcat 6 and JRebel used for rapid development.
- Determined performance enhancements using JVisualvm.
- Provided developer support for Microsoft SQL Server administration.
- Developed a CentOS VirtualBox image allowing developers to work and solve issues using production OS configuration

TMX Finance

Sr. Software Engineer

June 2015 - February 2016 (9 months)

Technical lead for one of three squads assigned to consolidate 5 POS systems into one POS. The application uses JSPs, Spring MVC, Oracle, Hibernate, iBatis, EJBs, and JBoss. Accomplished several items to assist with the productivity of the these squads:

- Created a comprehensive Windows development vApp using VMWare to reduce the time required for new developers to become productive.
- Created a comprehensive Redhat development vApp using VMWare to reduce the time required for linux developers needing a run level 5 desktop to become productive.
- Installed a Nexus OSS server for developers to perform Maven deploys.
- Developed and provided project level WIKI to improve communication with all interested parties including developers, QAs, BAs, Compliance, and project management.
- Designed and developed a Restful Spring Boot micro service to interface to a
 consumer regulatory agency in Illinois for all TMX installment loans. The service
 tracks loan state transitions accepting simple JSON posts from the POS UI which are
 then converted into JAXB calls to the Veritec service.
- Recommended several process enhancements to improve the organization of Git repositories for micro services, Maven builds and versioning, Agile project structures and backlogs in TFS.
- Introduce VisualVM to monitor JVMs for performance and debugging.

Avaya

Sr. Software Engineer

June 2000 - May 2015 (15 years 1 month)

2014 -2015 Scrum lead and developer to enhance and stabilize Product Connect operations application. The application provides expert tools and tier IV support associates to connect to and support the majority of Avaya's installed products. The Connect application enforces authentication, authorization, determines method of product access, and responds to any challenges as needed.

- Identified and resolved major production issues and bugs by remotely attaching VisualVM to primary server and tool processes
- Organized multiple backlogs into organized Task and Planning boards to improve team communication.
- Eliminated manual and custom developer environments by creating numerous Linux 6 VMs with a defined developer toolset.
- Converted the application to Maven and Nexus.
- Created a comprehensive developer script to compile, package, and deploy primary Connect Server, Client, and five supporting war files to TomcatEE. The script improved application development and testing turn around time and eliminated errors resulting from manual installs.
- Established a Subversion branching structure to support several streams of major enhancements to the application.
- Established automated Bamboo build plans and plan dependencies for all release versions of Subversion branch structure.
- Designed and created Connect Admin UI to monitor and alert any problems related to Connect Servers, Services, and Tools. The UI was created using JSF, Spring, Spring Security, Oracle Hibernate, AJAX push.

2011 – 2014 Scrum lead, developer, and primary contact to Product Owner for the design, development, and enhancement of the EVAT application. The ExpertNet Assessment Tool performs network assessments for Voice, Video, and TCP based streams. The project uses Agile methodology based on the Forge suite of tools from Atlassian.

- Tomcat 5.x and 6.x developed and deployed on CentOS 5.x and 6.x
- JSF 2.0, ICEFaces 3.2, XHTML Facelets, CSS, HTML, Eclipse Indigo and Juno IDEs
- Subversion source control, JIRA tracking, Greenhopper planning, Crucible reviews, Bamboo builds using Nexus, Confluence wiki
- JUnit test cases, JParser for test reporting, and Sonar for code analysis
- Postgresql 8.4, SQL Architect for modeling, iBatis persistence
- QoS reports developed using JFreeCharts and JFreeReports
- Spring Security 3.1.13 to implement client certificate and PAM based authentication, session registry for license tracking, and access authorization using standard roles
- Network routing using Cisco 1841 and 2611xm routers
- Network switching using Cisco 3550 and 3560 layer 3 switches, various layer 2 switches
- QoS configurations using DSCP, VLAN CoS, and trusted VLANs
- RPM used to build and provide installation artifacts from Bamboo
- Department presentation for best practices and procedures using Avaya Forge tools

2009 -2010 Participated in the design and development of Connect3 which involved migrating the legacy Connect2 product written in C to Java using Java NIO. The Connect product provides terminal emulation using suedo TTYs for SSH, TCP and PPP based access to a broad range of Avaya Products, switches, and gateways for support associates and Expert automation tools using modem and IP based connectivity.

- Java NIO for buffer management
- Serialized Spring Beans for defining product connection metadata properties.

- Java queries to LDAP servers for device access authorization.
- Device specific connection information stored in Oracle with access using direct JDBC, Hibernate, and CXF web services.
- Ticket issue tracking information access using Siebel land Remedy SOAP web services.

2008 - 2009 Technical lead for the design and development of SAL Enterprise web interface which provides a dashboard summary and detail views of Avaya SAL gateways and product devices. Established the Spring, Java, and web document framework prior to scaled up UI development. The application was developed for JBoss and WebLogic heavyweight container deployments and uses JSF components from IceFaces, Facelets, EJB3, Hibernate, and JPA.

- JBoss 5.x and WebLogic 9 and 10 deployed to Solaris and Redhat linux
- JSF 1.2, Servlet JSP, ICEFaces 1.8, CSS, HTML, MyEclipse IDE
- Clear Case source control and Clear Quest issue tracking
- Spring Security 2.5 to implement client certificate, Radius, and LDAP based authentication

2007 – 2008 Technical lead for the design and development of the ESP Customer Portal. The portal allows Avaya customers to access multiple ticketing systems, SRM software release management information, and customer product inventory. The application is deployed to Tomcat's lightweight application using Spring web services with Hibernate for data access, Facelets, and JSF components by IceFaces

2005 – 2006 Participated in the development of Device Discovery and SNMP trap Correlation and Consolidation using Smarts InCharge application suite. The discovery functions of the application involved making several Avaya products fully discoverable and representing the data in Smarts CIM common information moidel

2000 – **2004** Technical lead for the design and development of a JEE application which manages the provisioning of voice and mail access for numerous target platforms. The application was based on JSPs and servlets deployed to WebLogic domains. Responsible for transitioning all Tibco based messaging to JMS and full automation of builds using Ant.

Sprint Nextel

```
Software Engineer
March 1999 - May 2000 (1 year 3 months)
```

Participated in the design and development of a web-enabled order entry system using EJB's and CORBA in the VisualAge development environment. The project was one of the first n-tiered efforts in a new corporate architecture requiring the development of a new framework to access legacy data. Responsibilities also included deployment and support of components for WebLogic's application server.

AnswerThink

```
Software Engineer
March 1998 - March 1999 (1 year 1 month)
```

Participated in the design and development of a web-enabled trouble reporting system for a telecommunications company using fast CGI in a Solaris environment. Responsible for developing business objects to encapsulate multiple legacy systems using C++ and Rouge Wave.

USAA

```
Software Engineer
August 1991 - March 1998 (6 years 8 months)
```

Member of corporate utilities group and participated in the design and development of a CORBA-like broker and transaction manager to access IMS and DB2 databases from client applications. Designed as a three-tier framework for OS/2 and MVS using Smalltalk, C++, C, and APPC. The design was constructed as a two-tier tactical solution and later ported to NT and AIX using Rogue Wave. The NT client applications use COM primarily to interface with the data broker. The COM layer has been ported to Visigenic's Corba broker for use by clients on unix.

Price Waterhouse Management Consultants

Manager

May 1990 - August 1991 (1 year 4 months)

Team lead for the design and modification of an oil and gas production accounting system for a large public company using DB2 and Telon. Responsible for a team of six during the design and construction phases.

KPMG

Consultant / Manager December 1983 - May 1900 (6 years 5 months)

Technical manager and architect for a new water utility system. The development project used CASE technology with Oracle and VMS. Responsible for developing the logical and physical data models, system architecture, and technical standards

Designed, enhanced, and implemented a customer information and accounting system. The system is implemented at a major southwest water utility.

Designed, enhanced, and implemented a revenue accounting system at a large independent oil company. The system implementation was performed in an IBM 3083 MVS/XA environment.

EDUCATION

- BBA The University of Texas at Austin 1975 1979
- Sun Certified Java Architect 2000